Mumford, Lewis (A Tribute), 1979-1982: An Inventory.
A Tribute to Lewis Mumford: An Inventory
1979-1982
Special Collections, Frances Loeb Library, Graduate School of Design, Harvard University.
DES.1998.0001.008170002
Mumford, Lewis, 1895-; Haar, Charles Monroe, 1920 -; Kayden, Jerold S. Lincoln Institute of Land Policy.
1 linear feet
Extent is approximate
Organizational files, including invitations, correspondence, photographs and the texts of tributes to Lewis Mumford, assembled by Charles M. Haar and Jerold S. Kayden. Haar and Kayden were organizers of the events celebrating Mumford as the first recipient of The Lincoln Institute of Land Policy Award.
Acquisition Information
Immediate source of acquisition: Gift of Jerold S. Kayden, 1998.
Conditions on Use and Access
Contact Special Collections Department, Frances Loeb Library, Harvard Design School
Biography
Lewis Mumford (1895-1990) was a notable and prolific writer and critic, best-known for his studies of urban life, architectural history, and the effects of technological development on human societies and cultures. Mumford was architectural critic for The New Yorker Magazine for over thirty years and was a founding member of the Regional Planning Association of America. Mumford’s work as a journalist was supplemented by numerous books, including The Brown Decades, The Myth of the Machine and The City in History (winner of the National Book Award). Among Mumford’s many awards was the the Presidential Medal of Freedom, which he received in 1964.
The collection includes correspondence and announcements related to the award dinner, the texts of tributes contributed by guests, and photographs of the dinner/award ceremony. Notes: The edited “proceedings” of the event was published as A Tribute to Lewis Mumford: First Recipient, Lincoln Institute of Land Policy Award, 1979-1980 (Cambridge, Mass: Lincoln Institute of Land Policy, 1982).
The collection is composed of of Series IA-IB (Correspondence/Acceptances/Regrets/Tributes), Series IC (Letters of Invitation), Series ID (Guest List & Program), Series IE (Correspondence.Mumford/Haar), Series IF (Miscellaneous Correspondence), Series IIA (Remarks by Lewis Mumford), Series III (Photographs), Series IV (Photographs of Boghosian collage), Series VA (Text as published), Series VB (Clippings file), Series VC (TM Lewis Mumford: A Bibliography//Elmer S. Newman).
- Tribute to Lewis Mumford / Correspondence/ Acceptances/ Tributes, / Date(s): 1979-1982; IA; / Quantity: 58.0
  Note: Letters of acceptance to the testimonial dinner honoring Lewis Mumford.
  Note: Many of the acceptances are accompanied by the texts of the tributes delivered at the dinner and which were subsequently published.
- Tribute to Lewis Mumford / Correspondence/ Regrets/ Tributes, / Date(s): 1979-1982; IB; / Quantity: 39.0
  Note: Letters of regret; regrets refer either to attendance at the dinner and/or inability to prepare a text for publication.
- Tribute to Lewis Mumford / Letters of Invitation, / Date(s): 1979; IC; / Quantity: 1.0
  Note: Drafts of letter of invitation to the dinner honoring Lewis Mumford, drafted by Charles M. Haar.
- Tribute to Lewis Mumford / Guest List & Program, / Date(s): 1979; ID; / Quantity: 1.0
- Tribute to Lewis Mumford/Correspondence/Lewis Mumford/Charles M. Haar, / Date(s): 1979-1980; IE; / Quantity: 11 items
  Note: Correspondence exchanged between Mumford and Haar relating to the award and related events.
- Tribute to Lewis Mumford/ Miscellaneous correspondence, / Date(s): 1979; IF; / Quantity: 4 items
  Note: Miscellaneous correspondence concerning the Mumford event.
- Tribute to Lewis Mumford/ Response [Remarks] by Lewis Mumford, / Date(s): 1979; IIA; / Quantity: 1 item
  Note: Annotated and corrected draft of Mumford's response to the Lincoln Land Institute's award. Includes autobiographical commentary.
- Tribute to Lewis Mumford/Photographs, / Date(s): 1979; III; / Quantity: 52 items
  Note: Group and individual photographs, as well as contact sheets and negatives, taken at the Mumford tribute.
  Note: Identified and recognized indivdiduals have been cited in the index.
- Tribute to Lewis Mumford / Photographs of Boghosian Collage, / Date(s): 1979; IV; / Quantity: 7 items
  Note: Prints and negatives of collage designed to honor Mumford by Varujan Boghosian.
- Tribute to Lewis Mumford/Published text, / Date(s): 1979; VA; / Quantity: 1 item
  Note: Text as published, including tributes, Mumford's statement and selected photographs.
- Tribute to Lewis Mumford / Clippings, / Date(s): 1977 - 1979; VB; / Quantity: 5 items
  Note: Miscellaneous clippings by and concerning Mumford.
- Tribute to Lewis Mumford/ LEWIS MUMFORD: A BIBLIOGRAPHY//Elmer S. Newman, / Date(s): 1971; VC; / Quantity: 1 item
  Note: Photocopy of Newman bibliography.
Personal Names Index
-- Photographs III
Bacon, Edmund -- Correspondence IA
Barnes, Edward L., 1915- -- Correspondence IB
Barry, Marion S. -- Correspondence IA
Bell, Daniel, 1916- -- Correspondence IA
Bell, David E. -- Correspondence IB
Biddle, Livingston L., 1918- -- Correspondence IA
Blake, Peter -- Correspondence IA, IB
Boghosian, Varujan -- Photographs III, IV
Bok, Derek -- Correspondence IA
Bok, Sissela -- Correspondence IB
Boorstin, Daniel J. -- Correspondence IA
Bridenbaugh, Carl -- Correspondence IB
Brown, Denise Scott-, 1921- -- Correspondence IA
Byrne, Jane, 1933- -- Correspondence IB
Campbell, Robert -- Correspondence IA
Catalano, Eduardo, 1917- -- Correspondence IB
Chase, Stuart, 1888-1985 -- Correspondence IA
Clay, Grady -- Correspondence IA
Cohen, Harold L. -- Correspondence IA
Coleman, William T., jr -- Correspondence IA
Commager, Henry Steele, 1902- -- Correspondence IA
Cook, Charles C. -- Correspondence IB
Cori, Carl Ferdinand, 1896- -- Photographs III
Cousins, Norman, 1912- -- Correspondence IA
Davis, Arthur -- Correspondence IA
Doebele, William A. -- Correspondence IA
Dubos, Rene Jules, 1901- -- Correspondence IA
Duffey, Joseph -- Photographs III
Duffey, Joseph D -- Correspondence IA
Dukakis, Michael Stanley, 1933- -- Correspondence IA
Duncan, Otis Dudley -- Correspondence IB
Eldredge, H. Wentworth -- Correspondence IA
Embry, Robert C. -- Correspondence IA
Fisher, Joseph -- Correspondence IB
Fitch, James Marston -- Correspondence IA
Fitch, Lyle Craig -- Correspondence IA
Fuller, R. Buckminster, 1895- -- Correspondence IB
Gans, Herbert J. -- Correspondence IA
Glazer, Nathan -- Correspondence IA
Goldschmidt, Neil -- Correspondence IA
Goodman, Percival -- Correspondence IA
Goodman, Percival -- Photographs III
Gottmann, Jean -- Correspondence IB
Graubard, Stephen -- Correspondence IB
Haar, Charles Monroe, 1920- -- Correspondence IC, IE, IF
Haar, Charles Monroe, 1920- -- Organization files (Collection)
Haar, Charles Monroe, 1920- -- Photographs III
Halprin, Lawrence -- Correspondence IA, IB
Handlin, Oscar, 1915- -- Correspondence IB
Hardee, Covington -- Correspondence IB
Harris, Patricia Roberts -- Correspondence IA
Huxtable, Ada Louise -- Correspondence IA
Jackson, Maynard -- Correspondence IA, IB
Jacobs, Jane, 1916- -- Correspondence IA, IB
Johnson, Philip C. 1906- -- Correspondence IA
Jones, Reginald -- Correspondence IB
Kayden, Jerold S. -- Correspondence IA, IF
Kayden, Jerold S. -- Organization files (Collection)
Kennedy, Edward M., 1932- -- Correspondence IA
Kepes, Gyorgy, 1906- -- Photographs III
Koch, Edward, 1924- -- Correspondence IA
Kristol, Irving -- Correspondence IB
Landrieu, Moon -- Correspondence IA
Lewis, Anthony, 1927- -- Correspondence IF
Lilienthal, David Eli, 1899-19819 -- Correspondence IB
Lincoln, David -- Photographs III
Llewelyn-Davies, Richard, 1912- -- Correspondence IA
Lynch, Kevin, 1918- -- Correspondence IA
Marcus, Norman, 1932- -- Correspondence IA
Marx, Leo, 1919- -- Correspondence IB
McCue, Gerald Mallon -- Photographs III
McHarg, Ian -- Correspondence IA
McKelvey, Blake, 1903- -- Correspondence IA
Menzies, Ian -- Correspondence IA, IA, IB
Meyerson, Martin -- Correspondence IA
Moltke, Willo von -- Correspondence IA
Morial, Ernest -- Correspondence IB
Mumford, Lewis, 1895- -- Bibliographies VC
Mumford, Lewis, 1895- -- Clippings files. VB, VB
Mumford, Lewis, 1895- -- Correspondence IE
Mumford, Lewis, 1895- -- Drafts IIA
Mumford, Lewis, 1895- -- Organization files (Collection)
Mumford, Lewis, 1895- -- Photographs III
Mumford, Lewis, 1895- -- Publications VA
Mumford, Sophie -- Photographs III
Newman, Elmer Simon, 1919- -- Bibliographies VC
Pei, I.M., 1917- -- Correspondence IB
Pell, Claiborne -- Correspondence IA
Perloff, Harvey -- Correspondence IB
Portman, John C. -- Correspondence IB
Reilly, William K. -- Correspondence IA
Reisman, David A. -- Correspondence IA
Reps, John -- Correspondence IB
Reuss, Henry S. -- Correspondence IA, IB
Riesman, David A. -- Photographs III
Rockefeller, David -- Correspondence IB
Schlesinger, Arthur, 1917- -- Correspondence IB
Scott, Mellier G. -- Correspondence IA
Sert, Josep Lluis, 1902-1982 -- Correspondence IB
Sert, Josep Lluis, 1902-1982 -- Photographs III
Sert, Josep Lluis, 1902-1983 -- Correspondence IA
Shapiro, Irving -- Correspondence IB
Stubbins, Hugh A., 1912- -- Correspondence IA
Thompson, Benjamin -- Correspondence IA
Tree, Marietta, 1917- -- Correspondence IB
Tsongas, Paul -- Correspondence IA
Tunnard, Lydia (Mrs. Christopher) -- Correspondence IB
Venturi, Robert -- Correspondence IB
Von Eckhardt, Wolf -- Correspondence IA
Warner, Sam Bass, 1928- -- Correspondence IB
Weaver, Robert C. -- Correspondence IA
Webber, Melvin -- Correspondence IB
Weese, Harry, 1915- -- Correspondence IA
Whyte, William A. -- Correspondence IA
Williams, Harrison A. -- Correspondence IA
Winnick, Louis -- Correspondence IB
Woolery, Arlo -- Photographs III
Corporate Names Index
Lincoln Institute of Land Policy -- Correspondence IC
Lincoln Institute of Land Policy -- Organization files (Collection)
Lincoln Institute of Land Policy -- Publications VA
LC Topical Headings Index
City planners--United States -- Organization files (Collection)
City planning--Awards -- Organization files (Collection)
Genre / Form Index
Bibliographies / VC
Clippings files. / VB
Collages / IV
Correspondence / (Collection), IA, IB, IC, IE, IF
Drafts / IC, IIA
Lists / ID
Organization files / (Collection)
Photographs / III, IV
Photographs / (Collection)
Programs / ID
Publications / VA
Testimonials / (Collection)
AAT Terms Index
City planners -- Organization files (Collection)